Some years ago,
منذ بضعة سنين
I stumbled across a simple design exercise
عثرت على تمرين بسيط في مجال التصميم
that helps people understand and solve complex problems,
يساعد الناس في حل المشاكل المعقدة،
and like many of these design exercises, it kind of seems trivial at first,
وكالكثير من تمارين التصميم هذه، يبدو هذا التمرين بسيطاً للوهلة الأولى،
but under deep inspection,
لكن عند التمعّن به،
it turns out that it reveals unexpected truths
تظهر حقائق غير متوقعة
about the way that we collaborate and make sense of things.
عن الطريقة التي نتعاون بها ونعطي معنى للأشياء.
The exercise has three parts
ينقسم التمرين إلى ثلاثة أجزاء
and begins with something that we all know how to do,
ويبدأ بشيء نعلم جميعًا كيفية القيام به،
which is how to make toast.
وهو كيفية تحميص الخبز.
It begins with a clean sheet of paper, a felt marker,
يبدأ التمرين بصفحة بيضاء وقلم،
and without using any words, you begin to draw how to make toast.
وبدون أي استخدام للكلمات، تبدأ برسم خطوات تحميص الخبز.
And most people draw something like this.
وقام معظم الأشخاص برسم أشياء كهذه.
They draw a loaf of bread, which is sliced, then put into a toaster.
رسموا شريحة من الخبز، ثم وضعوها في آلة التحميص.
The toast is then deposited for some time.
يبقى الخبز فيها لبرهة.
It pops up, and then voila! After two minutes, toast and happiness.
يتحمص الخبز! بعد دقيقتين، يخرج الخبز ويعم السرور.
Now, over the years, I've collected many hundreds of drawings of these toasts,
لقد قمت، على مدى سنوات عديدة، بجمع مئات الرسومات عن الخبز المحمص،
and some of them are very good,
وبعض هذه الرسومات جيدة جدًا،
because they really illustrate the toast-making process quite clearly.
لأنها تصور عملية تحميص الخبز بطريقة واضحة جداً.
And then there are some that are, well, not so good.
أما البعض الآخر فلم يكن موفقًا.
They really suck, actually, because you don't know what they're trying to say.
إنها سيئة جدًا، بالطبع، لأنك لا تفهم ما الذي تحاول قوله.
Under close inspection,
وعند التمعّن بها،
some reveal some aspects of toast-making while hiding others.
يظهر بعضها جوانب من عملية تحميص الخبز ويخفي بعضها جوانب أخرى.
So there's some that are all about the toast,
لكن بعض الرسومات تركز على كيفية تحميص الخبز بالتفصيل،
and all about the transformation of toast.
وعن عملية تحويله إلى خبز محمص.
And there's others that are all about the toaster,
وثمة رسومات أخرى تركز على آلة تحميص الخبز،
and the engineers love to draw the mechanics of this.
ويحب المهندسون رسم آلة تحميص الخبز بهذا الشكل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then there are others that are about people.
وثمة من يرسمون عن الأشخاص،
It's about visualizing the experience that people have.
ويجسدون من خلالها التجربة التي عاشوها.
And then there are others that are about the supply chain of making toast
وثمة رسوم أخرى عن خط إنتاج الخبز المحمص
that goes all the way back to the store.
الذي ينتهي في المخزن.
It goes through the supply chain networks of teleportation
يتم توريد الخبز المحمص عبر وسائل النقل
and all the way back to the field and wheat,
ومن ثم نعود إلى الحقل والقمح،
and one all actually goes all the way back to the Big Bang.
ثم نعود إلى نظرية الانفجار الكبير.
So it's crazy stuff.
يا للجنون!
But I think it's obvious
أظن أن من الواضح
that even though these drawings are really wildly different,
أنه على الرغم من أن هذه الرسومات تختلف عن بعضها بشكل كبير،
they share a common quality, and I'm wondering if you can see it.
إلا أن ثمة شيء مشترك فيما بينها، وأتساءل إن كنتم تلحظونه.
Do you see it? What's common about these?
أترونه؟ ما وجه الشبه بينها؟
Most drawings have nodes and links.
معظم الرسومات تحتوي على عقد وروابط.
So nodes represent the tangible objects like the toaster and people,
فالعقد إذًا تمثل الأشياء الملموسة مثل آلة تحميص الخبز والناس،
and links represent the connections between the nodes.
والروابط تمثل العلاقات بين العقد.
And it's the combination of links and nodes
وهي مزيج من الروابط والعقد
that produces a full systems model,
التي تنتج نموذجًا متكاملًا للأنظمة،
and it makes our private mental models visible
مما يجعل النماذج العقلية لدينا واضحة
about how we think something works.
عن آلية عمل شيء ما بنظرنا.
So that's the value of these things.
وهنا تكمن قيمة هذه الأشياء.
What's interesting about these systems models
ما يثير الإعجاب حول نماذج الأنظمة هذه
is how they reveal our various points of view.
أنها تكشف وجهات نظر عديدة.
So for example, Americans make toast with a toaster.
فعلى سبيل المثال، يحمِّص الأميركيون الخبز بآلة التحميص.
That seems obvious.
هذا يبدو جلياً.
Whereas many Europeans make toast with a frying pan, of course,
بينما يقوم الكثير من الأوروبيين بتسخين الخبز بالمقلاة، بالطبع،
and many students make toast with a fire.
ويحمّص الكثير من الطلاب الخبز بالنار.
I don't really understand this. A lot of MBA students do this.
يتعذر عليّ فهم هذا. الكثير من طلاب إدارة الأعمال يفعلون هذا.
So you can measure the complexity by counting the number of nodes,
يمكنكم إذًا قياس مدى تعقيد شيء ما عن طريق عدد العقد،
and the average illustration has between four and eight nodes.
ومتوسط عدد العقد يتراوح بين أربع إلى ثماني عقد.
Less than that, the drawing seems trivial,
حين يقل العدد عن ذلك، تبدو الرسمة سطحية،
but it's quick to understand,
لكنها تُفهم ببساطة،
and more than 13, the drawing produces a feeling of map shock.
أما عندما يزيد العدد عن 13، تصبح الرسمة أشبه بخريطة.
It's too complex.
هذا معقد للغاية.
So the sweet spot is between 5 and 13.
الرسمة المثالية تتراوح عقدها بين 5 إلى 13.
So if you want to communicate something visually,
إذا أردت التواصل مع شيء بصريًا،
have between five and 13 nodes in your diagram.
اجعل عدد العقد بين 5 و 13 في رسمك البياني.
So though we may not be skilled at drawing,
إذًا بغض النظر عن امتلاكنا مهارة الرسم،
the point is that we intuitively know how to break down complex things
الأهم أن نعلم بديهيًا كيف نحلل الأمور المعقدة
into simple things and then bring them back together again.
إلى أشياء بسيطة ثم نعيد دمجها مجددًا.
So this brings us to our second part of the exercise,
هذا يحيلنا إلى القسم الثاني من التمرين
which is how to make toast,
المتمثل بكيفية تحميص الخبز،
but now with sticky notes or with cards.
لكن الآن بواسطة الملاحظات اللاصقة أو البطاقات.
So what happens then?
ما الذي حدث إذًا؟
Well, with cards, most people tend to draw clear, more detailed,
معظم الذين يستخدمون البطاقات يميلون إلى رسم عقد واضحة
and more logical nodes.
وأكثر منطقية وتفصيلًا.
You can see the step by step analysis that takes place,
تستطيعون مشاهدة التحليل أمامكم خطوة بخطوة،
and as they build up their model, they move their nodes around,
وفي أثناء بناء نموذجهم يقومون بتحريك العقد،
rearranging them like Lego blocks.
ويعيدون ترتيبها تماماً كأحجار الليغو.
Now, though this might seem trivial, it's actually really important.
قد يبدو هذا سطحياً، لكنه كبير الأهمية بالفعل.
This rapid iteration of expressing and then reflecting and analyzing
فهذا التكرير السريع في التعبير والتفكير والتحليل
is really the only way in which we get clarity.
هو الطريقة الوحيدة التي توضح الأمور أمامنا.
It's the essence of the design process.
إنه جوهر عملية التصميم.
And systems theorists do tell us
ويخبرنا أصحاب نظريات الأنظمة
that the ease with which we can change a representation
أن سهولة تغيير العرض التوضيحي
correlates to our willingness to improve the model.
ترتبط برغبتنا في تحسين النموذج.
So sticky note systems are not only more fluid,
إذًا فأنظمة الملاحظات اللاصقة ليست أكثر سلاسة وحسب،
they generally produce way more nodes than static drawings.
بل إنها تنتج عمومًا مزيداً من العقد مقارنة بالرسوم الثابتة.
The drawings are much richer.
إنّ الرسومات أغنى وأكثف.
And this brings us to our third part of the exercise,
وهذا يحيلنا إلى القسم الثالث من التمرين،
which is to draw how to make toast, but this time in a group.
وهو كيفية رسم طريقة تحميص الخبز، لكن ضمن مجموعة من الناس.
So what happens then?
ما الذي يحدث إذاً؟
Well, here's what happens.
إليكم ما يحدث.
It starts out messy, and then it gets really messy,
تبدأ العملية عشوائيًا، ثم تصبح أكثر فوضى،
and then it gets messier,
وتزداد الفوضوية،
but as people refine the models,
لكن عندما يقوم الناس بصقل النماذج،
the best nodes become more prominent,
تصبح أفضل العقد هي المسيطرة أكثر،
and with each iteration, the model becomes clearer
ومع كل تكرير، يصبح النموذج أوضح.
because people build on top of each other's ideas.
لأن الناس تبني أفكارها فوق أفكار الآخرين.
What emerges is a unified systems model
وينتج أخيرًا نموذج أنظمة موحد
that integrates the diversity of everyone's individual points of view,
يدمج وجهات النظر المتنوعة لكل شخص،
so that's a really different outcome
إذًا هذه حصيلة آراء مختلفة
from what usually happens in meetings, isn't it?
مما ينتج عن الاجتماعات، أليس كذلك؟
So these drawings can contain 20 or more nodes,
يمكن لهذه الرسومات أن تحتوي على 20 عقدة أو أكثر،
but participants don't feel map shock
لكن المشاركين لا يشعرون بتعقيد الأمر
because they participate in the building of their models themselves.
لأنهم شاركوا في صناعة نماذجهم بأنفسهم.
Now, what's also really interesting, that the groups spontaneously mix
المثير للإعجاب أيضًا هو أن المجموعات مُزجت من تلقاء نفسها
and add additional layers of organization to it.
وأضافت إليها طبقات إضافية من التنظيم.
To deal with contradictions, for example,
للتعامل مع التناقضات، على سبيل المثال،
they add branching patterns and parallel patterns.
يقومون بإضافة أنماط وأنماط موازية.
Oh, and by the way, if they do it in complete silence,
وبالمناسبة، إذا قاموا بذلك بصمت مطبق
they do it much better and much more quickly.
فإنهم يفعلون ذلك بشكل أفضل وأسرع أيضًا.
Really interesting -- talking gets in the way.
أمر مثير حقًا -- التكلم يعيق طريقهم.
So here's some key lessons that can emerge from this.
إليكم بعض الدروس الهامة التي تنبثق عن هذا.
First, drawing helps us understand the situations
أولاً، الرسم يساعدنا في فهم المواقف
as systems with nodes and their relationships.
كالأنظمة ذات العقد وعلاقاتها.
Movable cards produce better systems models,
تنتج البطاقات المتحركة نماذج أنظمة أفضل،
because we iterate much more fluidly.
لأننا نقوم بالتكرير بسلاسة أكبر.
And then the group notes produce the most comprehensive models
ثم تنتج عقد المجموعة أكثر النماذج شمولية
because we synthesize several points of view.
لأننا نقوم بتوليف وجهات نظر متعددة.
So that's interesting.
هذا مثير للفضول.
When people work together under the right circumstances,
عندما يعمل الناس سوية في الظروف الصحيحة،
group models are much better than individual models.
فإن نماذج المجموعة تكون أفضل من النماذج الفردية.
So this approach works really great for drawing how to make toast,
هذا المنهج يعمل جيدًا عند رسم عملية تحميص الخبز،
but what if you wanted to draw something more relevant or pressing,
لكن ماذا إذا كنت تريد رسم شيء يتعلق بك أكثر؟
like your organizational vision, or customer experience,
مثل الرؤية التنظيمية أو تجربة العميل
or long-term sustainability?
أو الاستمرارية على المدى الطويل؟
There's a visual revolution that's taking place
ثمة ثورة بصرية تحدث الآن
as more organizations are addressing their wicked problems
بينما تقوم المزيد من المنظمات بمعالجة مشاكلها المستعصية
by collaboratively drawing them out.
عن طريق التعاون على رسم المشاكل.
And I'm convinced that those who see their world as movable nodes and links
وأنا مقتنع أن هؤلاء الذي يرون عالمهم كعقد وروابط متحركة
really have an edge.
يحدثون تقدمًا حقيقيًا.
And the practice is really pretty simple.
والتمرين بسيط للغاية.
You start with a question, you collect the nodes,
تبدأ بسؤال، ثم تجمع العقد،
you refine the nodes, you do it over again,
تقوم بتنقية العقد، ثم تكرر الأمر ثانية.
you refine and refine and refine, and the patterns emerge,
تقوم بالتنقية مراراً وتكراراً إلى أن تظهر الأنماط
and the group gets clarity and you answer the question.
وتتوضح الأمور أمام المجموعة ثم تقوم أنت بالإجابة على السؤال.
So this simple act of visualizing and doing over and over again
هذا العمل البصري البسيط والقيام به مرارًا وتكرارًا
produces some really remarkable outcomes.
يقود لنتائج ذات أهمية كبرى.
What's really important to know
من الجدير أن تعلموا
is that it's the conversations that are the important aspects,
أن الأهمية الحقيقة تكمن في الحوارات،
not just the models themselves.
وليس في النماذج وحسب.
And these visual frames of reference
وهذه الأطر البصرية التي تشكل مرجعًا،
can grow to several hundreds or even thousands of nodes.
يمكن أن تتطور إلى مئات بل آلاف العقد.
So, one example is from an organization called Rodale.
مثال من منظمة تدعى (روديل)،
Big publishing company.
وهي شركة نشر كبرى.
They lost a bunch of money one year,
خسروا الكثير من المال في سنة واحدة،
and their executive team for three days visualized their entire practice.
وقام فريقهم التنفيذي على مدار ثلاثة أيام بتصوير ممارساتهم بالكامل.
And what's interesting is that after visualizing the entire business,
وما يثير الفضول أنه بعد تصوير العمل بأكمله،
systems upon systems,
نظاماً تلو آخر،
they reclaimed 50 million dollars of revenue,
بلغت عائداتهم 50 مليون دولار،
and they also moved from a D rating to an A rating from their customers.
كما تحركوا من تقييم D إلى تقييم A من قبل زبائنهم.
Why? Because there's alignment from the executive team.
لماذا؟ لأن الأمور عادت إلى نصابها على يد فريقهم التنفيذي.
So I'm now on a mission to help organizations
أنا الآن في مهمة مساعدة المنظمات
solve their wicked problems by using collaborative visualization,
لحل مشاكلها المستعصية عن طريق استخدام التصور المشترك،
and on a site that I've produced called drawtoast.com,
وثمة موقع أنشأته يدعى drawtoast.com،
I've collected a bunch of best practices.
جمعت فيه عددًا من أفضل التمارين.
and so you can learn how to run a workshop here,
يمكنكم من خلاله تعلم كيفية إنشاء ورشة عمل،
you can learn more about the visual language
كما يمكنكم تعلم المزيد عن اللغة البصرية
and the structure of links and nodes that you can apply to general problem-solving,
وبناء الروابط والعقد التي يمكنكم تطبيقها لحل أي مشكلة تعترضكم،
and download examples of various templates
ويمكنكم تحميل أمثلة متنوعة
for unpacking the thorny problems that we all face in our organizations.
لتحليل المشاكل العالقة التي نواجهها في منظماتنا.
So the seemingly trivial design exercise of drawing toast
تمرين رسم عملية تحميص الخبز يبدو سطحيًا،
helps us get clear, engaged and aligned.
لكنه يساعدنا في توضيح المشكلة وتنظيمها.
So next time you're confronted with an interesting challenge,
فإذا واجهتم تحديًا مثيرًا بعد الآن،
remember what design has to teach us.
تذكروا ما يمكن أن نتعلم من التصميم.
Make your ideas visible, tangible, and consequential.
اجعلوا أفكاركم مرئية وملموسة ومترابطة منطقيًا.
It's simple, it's fun, it's powerful,
الطريقة بسيطة وممتعة وناجعة.
and I believe it's an idea worth celebrating.
وأعتقد أنها فكرة تستحق الاحتفال.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)